Matt Walsh and Nick Carter are partners at Castle Island Ventures.
All of these expressed by them or the guests on this podcast are solely their opinions
and do not reflect the opinions of Castle Island Ventures.
Guests and hosts may maintain positions in the assets discussed in this podcast.
You should not treat any opinion expressed by anyone on this podcast as a specific inducement
to make a particular investment or follow a particular strategy, but only as an expression
of their personal opinion.
This podcast is for informational purposes only.
Brought down by Bad Mortgage Investments, Lehman, which has 25,000 employees, will be liquidated.
The federal government loans American International Group, AIG, $85 billion.
This is a different kind of market and the Fed is asleep.
The federal government is stepping in to stabilize Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac, the two mortgage
giants that have been threatened by the housing crisis.
The Bank of England has pumped 75 billion pounds more into Britain's ailing economy
with a new round of quantitative easing.
You print a couple trillion dollars and all of a sudden people start to worry.
So out of this worry, we have something called the Bitcoin, Bitcoin.
The story of Maple Protocol is a comeback story that in many ways mirrors the journey
of DeFi capital markets itself.
Maple founder Sid Powell left his career in traditional debt markets in 2019 to build
a more efficient crypto lending platform.
At the time, BlockFi and Celsius had emerged as early crypto lenders using off-chain underwriting,
while Maker and Compound had surfaced as nascent DeFi market entrants.
Powell had seen the inefficiencies of the traditional banking system up close and became
interested in the concept of capital formation outside of these traditional guardrails.
Maybe stable coins and smart contracts could remove some of the friction in underwriting
and lending and institutional grade credit could exist on chain with faster moving capital
formation and a far wider set of market participants.
Maple launched in 2021 with that vision in mind, to offer high quality DeFi credit opportunities
in a way that felt credible and compliant.
For a while, that bet was paying off as Maple gained momentum and delegates, delegates being
expert credit underwriters on Maple's platform and were consistently underwriting loans to
trading firms and market makers.
Maple was facilitating hundreds of millions in originations and for those watching from
the outside, it felt like the protocol had reached escape velocity.
Unfortunately, 2022 proved a difficult year.
The crypto credit contagion unfolded at scale from Celsius and BlockFi to the FTX fallout
and Maple found itself caught in this storm.
Major borrowers defaulted, including orthogonal trading and the full structure of the protocol's
first iteration was tested all at once.
Pool delegates were caught off guard, lenders suffered losses and TVL suffered.
For Powell, the founder of a now distressed protocol with a live token and real users,
the path forward was difficult and opaque.
On great adversity, Powell and the Maple team got to work forging a path forward.
That process started with a retrospective of what went wrong, what was salvageable and
what risk parameters would be sustainable over the long term future.
The team quickly identified areas for potential change.
They tightened the underwriting process and implemented stricter requirements for pool
delegates.
They also launched a new product called Syrup, a permissionless lending primitive that allows
users to earn yield on stablecoins without relying on a human underwriter, a delegate.
Instead of curated delegates, Syrup uses standard risk parameters and smart contract logic to
manage loans, making it significantly more scalable and accessible for a wider set of
lenders and borrowers.
This was a meaningful shift, a move away from centralized underwriting and towards more
scalable rules-based infrastructure.
This wasn't an overnight turnaround and trust had to be earned back gradually, keeping in
mind that most other lenders from 2022 had completely gone away.
Maple initially re-entered the market quietly, with a focus on reliable, stablecoin-native
credit and institutional-grade partners.
Over time, TVL began to return and new borrowers came online.
Perhaps most importantly, the protocol separated itself from the CFI collapse that had defined
the previous cycle.
In typical slowly-than-all-at-once fashion, Maple made its way to $500 million in deposits
by late 2024, no small feat, and then found true escape velocity in the spring of 2025.
Today, Maple has over $3 billion in deposits.
The platform offering now looks very different from its first iteration, more streamlined,
risk-aware, and focused.
As DeFi credit markets show sign of maturity in the backdrop of the ongoing stablecoin
boom, Maple is once again at the forefront of defining what institutional capital market
formation could look like.
In this conversation, Sid and I discuss on-chain credit broadly and Maple's path to becoming
a market leader in stablecoin-powered debt markets.
I hope you enjoy our conversation.
Sid, thank you for joining us today.
I wanted to say from the outset, one thing I admire about you and the team at Maple is
for as long as I've known you in the protocol, it feels like while there have been inflection
points in growth and there have been times when things have been slower, I don't see
you guys as having changed attitude in any way.
It seems like you've been fairly consistent in what you've been trying to do throughout.
Yeah, I think that's pretty accurate.
First of all, thank you for having me on.
I've listened for a long time, so it's good to finally be on the show.
But I do think we do treat it as kind of a job, rather than something where you one day,
some days you wake up and you have kind of the passion for it and you show up to work
and some days you don't and you stay in bed.
We've always viewed it as a profession and so we try and show up and do the job whether
we like it day in or day out.
Some days it's worse than others and you don't feel like doing it, but you still put on one
boot at a time and show up and do it to a professional degree.
We did that through the end of 2022 when things are really bad and into 2023 and then we still
do it now.
We haven't changed the way or the pace that we work at just because times are much better
now.
And a point that I'd highlight is I don't think there are many teams that have been
around for that kind of time span, having had a moment where you had to refocus almost
or readjust without having completely pivoted into a different category.
A lot of these things became restaking protocols one day or went from NFTs to some sort of
modularized lending one day and you guys really stayed true to the credit and capital markets
direction.
Yeah.
I think we have tried to do that.
Actually, just continuing the thought from the last question, I think two things that
kind of influenced me were I really like this book called What I Talk About When I Talk
About Running by Murakami.
He talks about how he gets up, he has a routine when he's writing a book and he gets up every
morning at like four or five in the morning and he writes for five or six hours, then
he eats, then he goes for a run in the afternoon and it's just like the craft is getting up
and just doing that every day whether he feels like it or not.
But on the pivot side, I think we've always thought that to really be successful, you
have to play in where you have an edge.
The closest we ever came to doing something kind of different was early 2023 when there
was the craze around tokenized T-bills.
We put out a product that was cash management, so it was still structured similar to how
we do the over collateralized lending, but the collateral for the loans was T-bills,
so the rate you could earn was about the T-bill rate.
What we found though was that it was very competitive.
We had very little way of differentiating ourselves and it was a race to the bottom
on fees.
So we kind of went back to our roots and for us, that is lending and credit and doing
that to institutions.
And what we observed was that the most contrarian bet you could take at the time in early to
mid 2023 was thinking that lending was going to come back.
Everybody was ready to totally write off the sector.
So we more looked at, okay, if we can't do under collateralized lending, which is what
we've done before, is there a form of lending we can do?
What is the market saying it will buy at the moment that it's not being sold or not being
offered?
And clearly it wasn't under collateralized lending at the time.
So what we did was we looked at over collateralized lending, where all the main competitors in
that segment had blown up or exited the space from the end of 2022.
And so we said, okay, we have the skills to do this.
Nobody else is doing it.
We can price it appropriately and we can get paid for it.
And we think over the long term, what are the odds that lending, the oldest service
in finance doesn't come back within this space?
Probably pretty low.
So that gave us the confidence, I think, to stick with lending as a segment instead of
trying to pivot and become a restaker or a tokenization platform or something else.
And I have seen a bunch of teams who pivot repeatedly and sometimes it's good to pivot.
Slack was a pivot, but sometimes you actually just want to stick it out and work out a different
way to kind of hit your same North Star.
It's pretty incredible.
I remember a time in there on 2023 when consensus view in the industry was probably that crypto
and CIFI didn't go well together and you had a coin base.
But in terms of something like lending, there was an intense skepticism around centralized
lending for crypto, which is nearly ludicrous in retrospect.
Yeah.
Some of the pain points to the criticisms of the centralized lending at the time, I think
were valid.
limited transparency and a lot of opaqueness around the performance of the loans.
Were they paying or not?
Were they collateralized or under collateralized?
What was the equity of the lending company?
So how much buffer did they have to absorb losses?
Well, those are more fairly valid criticisms, I think.
But it was taken to kind of an absurd degree, which was that lending is dead and doesn't
belong on blockchains in the sector and they just do it so much better in traditional finance.
If you read enough traditional finance history, you see Citibank blows up every 40 years.
So I don't know that they are doing it so much better than we can.
And I think in a new segment, you have to kind of make it up as you go along.
And you can take lessons from traditional finance, but you have to adapt it to what
is a nascent market.
You can't require every company that you deal with in crypto to have audited financials
by a big four accounting firm because that just doesn't exist.
So the consensus view was obviously very against lending, but that in turn created the
opportunity for us.
If the consensus hadn't been that lending was terrible and there were a bunch of people
coming in wanting to offer the same products we do now, then maybe we wouldn't have grown
the way that we have over the last 18 months.
It's like Howard Marks says, you have to be both non-consensus and correct.
If you're consensus and correct, you don't get paid.
And if you're non-consensus and wrong, you're toast.
You don't make anything.
Yeah.
You zero it out.
How much do you think some of those irresponsible credit activities in 2022, let's say, set
us back as an industry?
And was that purely a matter of individual actors making rash decisions and some accompanying
contagion?
Or how do you look back on that period and the mass fallout that we had?
Well, it definitely set us back, I'd say probably the rest of the duration of the Biden administration.
Certainly at least two years, because it's only now that some of the players who initially
had their own blockchain and on-chain project teams doing something, all those teams effectively
got shuttered.
And I would say it's only now that we've kind of come through to the Trump administration
where there is more of an appetite for the industry to be based in the US, that those
teams are getting restarted or those people are getting rehired again.
So I'd say at least two years, but it's always very difficult to kind of run a Schrodinger's
cat type scenario on the probability that didn't play out.
But to your other question, I hate it when somebody says the causes are multifactor.
I think it was due in a large respect to individual bad actors, but what kind of creates the condition?
And in some cases, people who are otherwise good, who just made incorrect decisions at
the time, but definitely there were cases of fraud, three arrows, Celsius.
But you have to kind of look at the conditions that create that, right?
The conditions that created are easy money.
Easy money is when more fraud happens.
And that is because money was getting pushed into venture and then from venture gas to
get pushed into investable businesses.
And what happened was that the lending companies got valued based on the size of their loan
book.
So if you gave out a bad loan, let's say you gave out $100 million of bad loans, you got
valued the same as a company that gave out $100 million of good loans, maybe more because
it's obviously easier to give out $100 million of bad loans than $100 million of good loans.
It takes longer, more rigorous underwriting.
And so those businesses could scale faster.
And the game was to get as big as possible so that you could revalue yourself and do
another equity round at a higher valuation.
So that bred bad behavior because there was no feedback mechanism to uncover who was swimming
naked until the end of 2022 after we had the lunar blow up and that uncovered a bunch of
holes in balance sheets.
And to a certain extent, that also drove things like FTX, right?
Sam SBF was doing a new round at 20 percent higher valuation every two or three months,
right? I remember at the start of 2022, I think he was raising it $10 billion.
By the end, it was $30 billion or just before the end of November.
So I think the massive amounts of liquidity in the system definitely created distortive
behaviors. But this is as Ray Dalio says, this is what you see in every credit bubble.
And this is why it's called a credit cycle.
And that's just what you have to watch out for the next time.
And I think the key in a lending business is that unlike other businesses, you have to
recognize that you never really hit escape velocity from being in a cyclical industry.
And so you always have to watch out that at any given cycle, you are still at risk.
Your business still faces an existential risk if you don't control your credit and your
underwriting and your risk management. And that's kind of unique to credit and lending
businesses in all of finance and startups.
It's not really the same in other sectors.
Yeah, that's it. I do worry about where we'll go to with some of the trends that I'd
argue are closer to easy money, like you'd say.
Like, I'm sure we'll get a leveraged Treasury equity vehicle, for example.
Yeah, we used to have those in Treadfy, right?
They used to lever up T-bills a lot.
I think they still do. But you will have, I think, a Treasury company that probably
leverages too much and maybe blows itself up.
But that will be driven by very easy, accommodative monetary conditions.
And so we have an advisor to the company and he's been in the lending business for a long
time. And so we catch up with him every few months and we kind of take stock of, on a
scale of one to ten, where are we in terms of credit conditions?
Ten being the worst and one being the most conservative.
And our sense at the moment is that we're still in kind of the first half.
It's still more like a four rather than like a seven or an eight or a nine.
Whereas mid-2022, you probably would have said that was more like a nine.
I remember at that time, rates borrowing against Bitcoin were getting down to like
two, three percent. Unsecured rates lending Bitcoin were 10 to 20 basis points.
And the dollar unsecured rates were six percent.
So fully unsecured lending.
Whereas here today, rates lending against Bitcoin overcollateralized are probably in
the seven to eight range.
So I'd say we're still in a much more conservative set of conditions.
And I don't see that kind of frothy euphoria that we did in 2022 yet.
Yeah, I tend to agree. Talking about some of these systems, how did you decide to go
and try and build DeFi credit markets?
Or what inspired you to move that direction, given your experience?
So my experience was I used to work in TranFi banking.
So I used to be in an area called securitization and debt capital markets.
This meant basically we issued bonds and we helped companies to issue bonds.
And that was how they borrowed. So they borrowed large amounts like, let's say,
five hundred million. And then they break that into small chunks and they make
five hundred thousand dollar loans.
So I always kind of had lending in the DNA, but I wanted to go to a more
entrepreneurial company from there.
So I went to a smaller commercial finance company that still exists in Australia
today. That was where I met my co-founder.
And the initial idea was to do tokenized bonds on chain.
So that was really tough.
There was no DeFi at the time that we started the company was kind of five or six
teams.
Was that for distribution or what inspired that?
The idea was that if you could lower the cost of issuing bonds, you could make it
possible for the longer tail of finance companies to come in and issue them.
Because at the time, it was more of the case that it was almost not worth
issuing securitized bonds if you couldn't do a hundred million at a time.
So you can see most companies were taking five years of operations to get there.
So you could just bring that forward and help those companies.
What we found, though, was there was nothing to tokenize on chain.
So all of DeFi was Maker, Set Protocol, Compound, Uniswap.
I don't think Aave had not rebranded from E-Flint at that point in time.
So really you had a very small on-chain ecosystem.
And so what we found was we instead had to go more of a direct lending route and look
to just lend to institutions who would borrow.
But the initial way that we wanted to do it was back in 2018, 2019, everybody was
obsessed with marketplaces.
You had to be an asset-like marketplace.
God forbid you're asset heavy because you're not going to make the same returns on
equity. As we tried doing that, and that was the initial iteration of Maple, was
you'd have other credit managers called delegates come on and they would earn a
FB, like an independent contractor, and we would earn a platform fee because
everybody wanted to be like Stripe or Uber or Airbnb, and you clip your platform
fee and other people take a portion of the revenue and then you're kind of neutral.
So you can scale much easier because you don't have to hire staff.
You just allow other people to sign up and use your infrastructure.
And that was kind of working out to begin with.
So we got the delegates up and running.
We thought that we would not have any reputational impacts if delegates had credit
issues with the loans they underwrote.
And we thought we would be able to scale much faster being a kind of asset-like
marketplace. And you get the asset-like marketplace multiples, right, in terms of
how people rate your company.
I think what you can see, though, in the time since then is that actually there's a
lot of value in being asset heavy.
Asset heavy is kind of a moat.
Vertical integration gives you pricing power.
To be vertically integrated, you just have to have more plant and equipment and
capital. And so that means you're asset heavy, but you get the pricing power and
the pricing power gives you longevity.
And you can see it in Apple.
Apple didn't say we want to be an asset light piece of hardware that supports any
kind of software, nor did they want to say we just want to have the app store and
it's on available on any hardware device.
They said, we've got to have the both of them.
And you can see that for them, they make all of the profits in the smartphone
sector, right, despite being a minority of the market.
And I think you can see it with Tesla as well.
They make their software, they make their hardware and across history, economic
history as well. You can see numerous examples of this going right back to
Standard Oil. And so I think that is how our model shifted over 2023.
We said, OK, we're going to remove the delegates.
We will be the sole kind of underwriter here and we will therefore control who
gets to borrow and we will actually be the borrower ourselves.
So we borrow from people who put capital on the platform and then we lend it out
and we keep a spread.
But it allowed us to move faster.
We doubled our revenue because we weren't paying our fees to third parties on the
platform. And I think over time, you can see that that's kind of proved
strategically the correct way to go.
Notwithstanding that a number of our venture backers at the time said this is
going to prevent you from scaling as fast as you could if you were just
infrastructure. And they have pointed to other lending markets that have grown
quite substantially over that period of time.
But I would say that there are some of those lending markets who make a lot of
revenue and are doing very well.
There are some who actually make no revenue despite being larger in terms of
TVL than us. And that's because other parties, they have weak negotiating
positions and other parties have effectively taken the majority of the
revenue there. So we have a better negotiating position.
And so I think vertical integration rather than just being a pure marketplace
is actually in the end, the better way to go.
Yeah, I think it's a great point.
There was such a push towards being asset light because I look at it as an
existential problem in DeFi that everyone sees themselves as just capital
aggregation layers or a capital marketplace without any actual tie to the
capital. But that makes it naturally very fleeting.
And then you had this idea of protocol owned liquidity, which I think made a lot
of sense in that vein of like, OK, you actually have some control of it for the
first time. Yeah, I think protocol owned liquidity gave teams a better balance
sheet and wasn't necessarily executed well by some of the teams that did it,
like Olympus. But the concept, I think, was sound.
But getting a balance sheet gives you heft and gives you negotiating power.
In the Web2 world, you can look at eBay, which continued to practice being asset
light. And then you can look at Amazon that built its own fulfillment centers.
And ultimately, the fulfillment centers allowed them to vertically integrate.
They could sell the good and then they could drop it to your house.
Whereas eBay relied on third parties for that.
And so the pricing power eventually finds its way to the third parties.
My view is that it's actually very important for teams to kind of vertically
integrate so that they get pricing power.
They have a balance sheet they can swing around.
And nowadays, we also get pitched a lot of deals where we can get extra spoken
incentives and things like that if we're lending to a certain company or
counterparty or partnering with them in some way, just because we now sort of
have that heft in terms of AUM in the pools.
So to summarize the conversation with regard to Maple, Maple was started as an
on-chain credit marketplace.
Is that how you would describe it today or how has the platform evolved and how
have you intentionally involved it?
So we would have started the marketplace.
I think the first thing we dropped was we became more of a lender and we started
marketing ourselves as a direct lender rather than a marketplace.
And the latest reimagining of what we are, reimagining is probably not the
right word, but the most apt description of what we are today is more of an
asset manager.
So we call ourselves an on-chain asset manager.
Our primary focus is lending and credit and yield.
And we run a couple of strategies.
The first and the largest is the over-collateralized lending.
So we are a secured lender to institutions.
We have a loan book of over a billion dollars and typically our loan sizes will
be anywhere from five mill at the low end to a hundred mill plus.
You know, we actually just did a hundred mill one today.
And then the other line is we have a BTC yield product.
So it's encompassed within the term asset manager, on-chain asset manager.
And if you look the TradFi peers or competitors, I would point to would be
Apollo, Aries, Blackstone.
These guys are the largest non-bank lenders in the world, but they don't
call themselves lenders.
What they call themselves is asset managers.
And I think we think about ourselves in the same vein.
We're an asset manager with a focus on credit and lending, and ultimately we
want to be competing with them.
Our view is that all lending over the next 10 years is going to be done in
stable coins, and so we are getting a leg up in kind of surfing that wave.
And that will bring with it cost advantages, distribution advantages,
speed advantages that will allow us to take share.
How do you create stickiness in the assets that you guys manage?
There's a couple of ways you can go.
So you can either do pricing or quality, I think.
And in lending and asset management, pricing is effectively, do you minimize
your own spread or deliver a higher yield to your customers?
But the other thing you can do is you can offer a lower volatility.
So more stability in that pricing.
And so I would say versus DeFi peers, we tend to produce a higher yield or return.
And a couple of the reasons for that is that we serve institutions who like
hosting BTC and native assets instead of wrapping those assets for a variety of
tax compliance and smart contract risk reasons, but we can offer that.
And your average DeFi protocol can't accept native Bitcoin.
And so the customers pay a little bit more for that.
We can also offer a qualified custody because we are more integrated
now with CFI providers like Anchorage, Bitgo, Coinbase, Custody, Zodiac
Custody, Fireblocks, and a number of other wallet and custody solutions.
Copper as well.
So that optionality, you also pay a premium for if you're an institutional client.
And so generally we deliver a higher yield than the DeFi lending protocols.
And so that's kind of pricing and quality, but we also tend to be
more stable over time because we don't have utilization-based rates.
We can offer fixed rates and again, institutions like to be able to lock
in certainty on their borrowing costs.
And so our rates don't fluctuate over time.
You'll never see a day where the maple rate goes from 6% to 9% and then the
following day is back at 4%, like you do on some of the DeFi protocols.
Many of them, I would add.
Yeah, it will be a steadier 6.5% to 7% over two months.
I've done some research on Apollo and some of these large credit firms.
And I would say roughly, let's say, cause they're in private credit, some 30, 40%
of what they allocate to is investment grade credit opportunities.
How would you compare where Maple is allocating as an asset manager to that set?
They are very fundamentally like we all fall within the ages of institutional
credit or private credit.
However, they have a $300 billion plus portfolio, so they're naturally going
to be doing a wider variety of things.
And they've built their business up over 40 years.
Apollo was started in the late eighties after Drexel Burnham by some
of the alumni from there.
And so they've had 40 years to build a very well diversified business.
And I would say our credit, we fall within the unrated category because the
company we lend to our primes, OTC desks, funds and exchanges, but we do
take what I consider to be very good quality collateral.
We're taking Bitcoin at trades over 50 billion a day, including Sundays.
And so we always have very good liquidity and downside protection when it comes to
that, but yeah, so I'd say it's institutional grade quality.
It's not rated yet by ratings agencies, but I do think that is going to be a
step that comes in in the next one to two years.
So my background was securitization.
I would love to start securitizing this stuff.
And I think that is ultimately how we're going to go and package Bitcoin backed
loans up and sell them to the next wave of investors who will come in, which
will be TradFi firms that don't necessarily want to buy an allocation to
loans done through a smart contract.
But what they might want to buy is a senior trench in a rated securitization
vehicle that has 200 Bitcoin backed loans sitting underneath it.
And that's ultimately where I think the puck is going over time.
And it brings in more capital, a wider set of investors, and ultimately
allows a firm like us to scale.
Securitizations is a major way that firms like Apollo and Aries and
Blackstone source their capital.
It's not just directly raising money into fund structures.
And because you guys are sourcing capital and stable coins and crypto assets, does
that give you unique opportunities in terms of who you can work with on the
borrower side?
Well, I think on the borrower side, there is just a natural preference to
borrow in stable coins.
Most of the firms who borrow today are typically using it for exchange
trading or arbitrage strategies.
And so you buy and sell Bitcoin in USDC or USDT, you're not doing it in
fiat for the most part, because you'll be doing it on an exchange.
And so there is a natural desire to borrow in stable coins.
But the advantage for us as the lender is I have zero marginal costs lending
to a trading desk based in Korea versus one in Miami or in London or in
Singapore, because it's the same cost to send that $10 million of stable
coins to them, which is very little.
And you can do it any time of day.
Whereas if we were sending them fiat, well, if that firm was in Hong Kong, it'd
be much harder for me to send it to them.
I'm going to have a banking infrastructure.
It's going to take multiple days to get to them.
And there's going to be a lot of fees taken by middlemen.
So I think stable coins are just so much better in terms of running a loan book.
And it's much easier to track as well.
It makes a ton of sense.
The 24 seven aspect is abundantly clear to me because it's one thing if I want to
go buy an asset and the market's closed.
It's another thing if some sort of financial service in Hong Kong needs a
line of credit instantly and they can't get it because markets are closed.
I don't know if you ever heard about the moon pay story when Trump coin launched
where they had to source, they had this weekend, insane interest rates.
It launched on Friday night, right?
Yeah.
And so lending in stable coins is basically the only way you can fund a
business like that when you have that short-term capital desire.
We, from time to time, do get pitches like that from payment processing firms.
That's not a line of business we do just yet because you're effectively
funding against receivables.
So there are things that can go wrong, but that kind of short duration, really
short notice, urgent credit, obviously you can make a lot of money if you have
the cash when those sorts of opportunities come up and having stable
coins is that easier way to deploy it.
One topic we've ran into is I think we'll get scenarios like that, especially
in crypto, as you have FX systems, stable coin systems, but it seems like a lot of
businesses would potentially prefer a revolving line of credit because they
have excess needs maybe at a certain moment when they have a lot of users on
ramping to an exchange or an influx of payments.
And I imagine that wouldn't be the preferred structure for someone like you guys.
So how do you think this shakes out?
Do you think that will be the need or demand of payments companies will be to
have a revolving line?
I think I want a revolving line.
The challenge with those, so I used to do them when I was in banking is you're
going to pay an un-drawn facility fee while you've got it, because if you
want to have the un-drawn line of credit for me, I've got to set aside that
capital so that I can send you the loan if you want to draw it down.
And it's really good for a lending company if you're at scale.
So if I have just a billion dollars in cash lying around and I have a bunch of
these firms who want $50 million lines of credit, and I know that most of the
time they're not going to be drawn and that really like, I'm always going to
have kind of $200 million of cash spare.
Then I'm totally comfortable doing this because it's just a creative to my
bottom line, like I had the cash there anyway, I may as well get paid something
for keeping it there, whereas we tend to run at a higher drawn level.
So my opportunity cost of keeping aside this 50 million cash for these guys is
that I could have been out there lending it for seven or 8%.
So that's typically where the un-drawn lines of credit get challenging.
As we get bigger, we will do things like un-drawn lines of credit because we'll
start to have scale in order to be able to do so, and there's naturally demand
for it because everybody wants the ability to call down capital at short
notice without having to pay an arm and a leg for it, and if they have to borrow
it, then they're going to pay 7% to 8% or higher, depending on what they
collateralize it with, and if they can keep it un-drawn, then they're only
paying 1% to 2%.
As Maple scales and maybe even say as on-chain asset management or capital
market scale, who have been the folks willing to deposit from early on and
be early adopters, and how do you think the adoption curve migrates?
I think the early adopters within the crypto space are always a combination
of high net worth individuals, and that can be in the form of known folks who
sign documents with you, or it can be in the form of some of those DAOs.
There are certain groups like DeFi Whales, Turtle DAO, and others that are kind
of now acting as almost cap intro or aggregators for some of these high net
worths, but I would say it's high net worths, and then the other one is
on-chain yield hedge funds.
So they will run more complex strategies and effectively they are getting paid
by their LPs to be able to navigate the complexities of smart contracts and
some of these on-chain yield offerings and manage the downside risk and do
looping strategies where they can, but that's the other core group who kind of
deposits into things like what we're offering, particularly when we had things
like points programs, token incentives, that type of thing, and then over time,
as your product matures and you can show a track record of not hitting losses and
being able to meet redemptions and things on time, where it migrates to is corporate
treasuries, family offices, protocol integrations, because they're more
comfortable putting their brand on top of yours and they're comfortable, they can
stand behind the risk of your platform.
And so nowadays we have more corporate treasuries who use our product.
We have protocols who integrate with us.
We are now across Solana as well, and so we're active on Solana lending
markets and our product Syrup USDC is now accepted as collateral on multiple
lending markets, and that's because it's viewed as a relatively safe asset compared
to other more volatile ones out there.
It's exciting to see the waves of comfort and you always have that early adopter
base, like you said, that can be individuals, people familiar with crypto.
In the scope of a lot of the directions you guys have gone that we've talked
about, how much has been influenced or informed by regulatory policy and
sentiment and how has that opened doors for you?
How has your trajectory mirrored effectively what you can and can't do?
It's a good question.
Your regulation kind of sets the boundaries of what you can and can't do
in certain markets, and it also acts as a bit of a speed break, if you will.
And so the core business, like Maple and Stowe, which we have two strategies,
blue chip and high yield, those are only offered to accredited investors within
the US, so you have to onboard with us, sign documents, show that you are an
accredited investor, and that was really driven by regulation.
And then we had an offshore product, which was set up to be more DeFi
friendly, integrated with DeFi protocols.
You can take the LP tokens and move them around DeFi.
And that was set up in the middle of last year, but walled off from the US.
And that was because of the regulatory clampdown on DeFi within the US and the
generally more hostile posture that was in place.
So that kind of effectively shaped this bifurcation where we have two key
product lines and one that is not available in the US at all.
So the regulation definitely plays a large role in shaping things, but I
would say, you know, it's like on the bowling lane, it kind of sets the guard
rails, you're still trying to get to the pins at the end, you just have to kind
of know your boundaries there.
And so for us, it didn't slow us down from trying to grow the lending
business, it just meant that when we launched this more DeFi friendly version
of the product, we couldn't make it available in the US and had to take a
different approach there.
Given your expertise in the segment, a lot of people seem to believe we're on
the breakout of institutional grade assets coming on chain in large form
beyond what we've seen in the past.
Are you aligned with this or do you think there is an element of overblown
expectation or how do you view that potential phenomenon?
I have a mixed view of it.
So I think empirically, yes, you're seeing more institutional assets coming
on chain, Biddle is minting more tokenized T-bills and Robinhood is going
to be bringing equity like derivatives for private companies on chain and
folks like Ondo are going to be tokenizing things like Tesla.
So Kraken is already doing that.
So empirically, yes, we are seeing that happening, but I think is that going to
trigger a wave of, let's say, massive new AUM coming on chain?
I think that's where I have more of an issue because they're taking an asset
that's already widely available off chain and just trying to sell it to the
on-chain investors who presumably made their way on chain because they were
looking for something else, right?
A lot of people on chain are still high net worth in developed markets, right?
As it is to say, because they were early on to adopting new technology and it is
generally investors in developed markets that go and adopt new technology first.
So a lot of those folks already had access to Tesla stock or other
institutional grade assets.
They can call up a Morgan Stanley banker and get access to private equity.
So I don't know that's the answer.
And I think what we're seeing is that there is a buy side problem there where
there's just not that much demand to buy or hold these assets on chain.
We're taking the other approach, which is we're saying, actually, we think a lot
of TradFi investors would be interested in Bitcoin backed loans because it's a
very good yield pickup versus T-bills.
It's pretty short dated and short duration.
So you can get your money back quickly.
The collateral and the downside protection is really good.
Trades 50 billion plus a day, even on Sundays.
And this is actually a pretty interesting asset that they can't ring up a Morgan
Stanley banker and get.
And so maybe if somebody is going to sell it, why shouldn't it be us and why
shouldn't they want to buy it?
Cantor decided that Bitcoin backed loans are interesting enough to start
originating and we think that other firms are going to see what they saw and
move in that direction as well.
So we're actually taking the inverse approach.
We think more TradFi money will come on chain or choose on chain underlying
assets like Bitcoin backed loans done in stable coins.
But the stampede that everyone expected to see of people buying equities on
chain, I think that's going to be slower to materialize.
I like that view and I completely agree.
It's as if there's business to be done on chain that hasn't been taken advantage
of by Wall Street versus vice versa.
Yeah, you got to find a niche, right?
That's kind of the key to competition or rather to avoiding competition.
Yeah.
Sid, thank you for joining us and for the insights.
I'm glad we had a chance to finally have you on.
Me too.
My pleasure, Wyatt.
Thanks for having me on.
Appreciate it.
Thanks for listening to another episode of On the Brink with Castle Island.
To find out more about Castle Island, visit castleisland.vc.
To listen to all of our podcast episodes, please go to onthebrink-podcast.com or
just click on the tab in our website.
Thanks for listening.